last week I uh posted a Blog on uh how
called how to fix um glute
imbalances and it was a very popular
post but one of the um readers posted a
question in the comments portion that
said how do I know if I have a glute
imbalance and this is a an important
question that I forgot to address and uh
it's easier to address in a a video
format so um I'm tailoring my answer are
towards uh fellow personal trainers and
strength coaches and and also physical
therapists um so anyway I'm going to
give you four different ways the first
and and a very effective way is to just
ask the client um usually people know
they can feel it and um a lot of times
um I'll have a client tell me like I
feel my left glute working more than my
right and then um I'll check and they're
totally right I mean like without a
doubt no no um there's no comparison so
um always make sure you ask you know ask
people do you feel your glutes working
evenly or do you feel the glute on the
left working just as hard as one on the
right and they usually know they have a
really good idea because it's you can
feel it and I've had I've had clients um
who um you know their glute works is
fires super hard on the one side and
then on the other side they do the same
exact exercise for the right side side
and it barely fires and it's weak and
flabby um um and and a lot of times
you'll see that one glute has a lot more
hypertrophy than the other so and you
know it makes sense because the one
activates a lot better so first way ask
the client second way and this is the
most effective way to me is through
palpation I remember uh years ago I
attended a conference and uh and
actually one of the world's uh most
popular strength co uh sorry um physical
therapist was was uh presenting and he
said I don't need to fill your glutes I
can tell by the way you move if you're
using your glutes or not and I've never
agreed with that um you know someone can
look fine and not use their glutes that
much in fact um stum Mill published a
strongman study in 2009 and he showed uh
with EMG he showed um the the glute EMG
activity of the strongman doing
different heavy lifts and the the best
strong man used his glutes he used them
earlier on and he used them to a greater
degree than the other lifters when they
lifted heavy stuff so just being strong
does not ensure that you're using your
glutes um but you know just watching
someone move you can't really tell for
sure if they're using their glute or not
be because you can be using more
hamstring you can be using more quads
more you know erector more adductor um
so uh so um palpation to me is the most
important way and here's how I check
through palpation you can do a lot of
different ways you can lay them down
prone like this and just have them lift
one leg up and I like I like to poke a
few different areas now another thing I
should address
um a lot it's is kind of a the area with
with uh personal trainers and strength
coaches because you would never want to
get sued for touching someone's glutes
um but I always say beforehand do you
mind if I poke your glutes to see if
they're working and I've I've never had
a client say no but I wouldn't ask if I
you know if I felt like the client was
really insecure or something like that
um I've always worked with people who
kind of know I'm the glute guy and
that's a lot of times that's what
they're coming to me for but I've I've
had no problems as long as you're very
professional and you're not creepy about
it um so anyway I'm a big believer in
palpations so I'll poke upper and lower
because the upper and lower glutes
function differently from one another so
you can lay them down prone have them
lift one leg up lift the other leg up
you can have them bend the knee and lift
one leg up and lift the other up um I
like the quadraped position better
though so just have them hold this
position and squeeze their glue GL as
hard as possible and then do it on the
other side you know feel them make sure
they're symmetrical you could also do s
side line
clams um those are easy ways to tell if
they're using their glute and you can
make sure check not only that it fires
equally during the movement but also
that it's equal in size um in you know
each side is symmetrical and
hypertrophy okay so that's palpation the
next category is
strength and um this is a if there's a
huge imbalance here but as I said
earlier someone can do a movement
correctly and not use their glute much
but if you do unilateral movements like
Bulgarian split squats um and say the
the individual can get 20 reps on one
side but only five with the other side
well their right side is obviously way
weaker than their left side um if if
they got 20 on the left and on the right
and so probably they have a weaker glute
but it could also be weaker quad weaker
hamstring weaker everything so you don't
know for sure that it's the glute but if
there's a big asymmetry with strength
then that's a problem for strength
imbalances though I like um looking at
true single leg movements because like
the Bulgarian split squat that's a
that's really it's not a true single leg
because you've got two points of support
here so for
true single leg you could do a pistol
squat like that you could do a skater
squat where you go like that or you can
do a single leg RDL you know like this
and you can make sure that their their
form look symmetrical and they're of the
same strength when you have someone with
a really really weak glute they will go
to do like a skater squad or something
or a pistol and you'll see them like
cave in so bad it's not even funny um so
usually you can tell through those
single leg movements um with their with
looking at their form and their strength
levels okay and then the last category
is symmetrical movement and so a lot of
times when you have someone with a
weaker glute you'll watch them Squat and
they'll you know they'll go like
this and
usually like let's say they go this way
they're
um it I have wrap my brain around this
completely I don't think that like if
they lean to the right side this means
their right side is definitely stronger
um I think it usually means that but it
also could be Mobility related they
could have different hip hip flexibility
or um like ankle mobility in one of the
legs but um anyway you can look at
symmetrical Movement Like squatting
movements to see if they shift into One
Direction so there are four different
ways to see if somebody does in fact
have a glute imbalance so make sure you
read the blog um that I wrote I'll I'll
include the link in the description of
this video but make sure you read that
blog as to how to fix it